So picking up here, sorry, let me just get to us. Okay,
so we're at the bottom of טז עמוד א Tez Amud Alef
and we pick up with, where are we? Okay. אמרי
רב אשי למימר. Amrei Rav Ashi L'meimar. No, sorry. Okay, now I'm
sorry.
תנו רבנן אין נידוי פחות משלושים יום. Tanu Rabbanan Ein Nidui Pachot
Mi-shloshim Yom. So we are
eight lines from the bottom, line starts with the word משלושים יום.
Mi-shloshim Yom. אין נידוי פחות משלושים יום. Ein Nidui Pachot Mi-shloshim Yom.
נידוי Nidui as we've already talked before is a minimum of 30
days. We discussed the issue about if somebody wanted to, if wanted
to reverse it sooner, but certainly the standard נידוי Nidui is 30
days.
ואין נזיפה. Ve-ein Nezifah. Now נזיפה, Nezifah, which is a type of
a like even a lighter form than נידוי, Nidui, and the גמרא
Gemara never fully explains what the practices of נזיפה Nezifah are, type
of a censure, excellent word, but that, it doesn't explain what the
practical practices of it are. The only thing we're going to see
in the גמרא Gemara is that it's of a shorter period. So
אין נזיפה, Ein Nezifah, and maybe it was the same practices but
fundamentally for a shorter period. And there is no נזיפה Nezifah פחות
משבעה ימים, Pachot Mi-shiva Yamim, less than seven days. דאף על פי
שאין ראיה לדבר זכר לדבר, De-af al pi she-ein ra'ayah la-davar zecher
la-davar, although there's no proof, there's a hint to it. שנאמר ואביה
ירוק ירק בפניה הלא תיכלם שבעת ימים. She-ne'emar Ve-aviha yarok yarak be-faneha
halo tikkalem shivat yamim. If her father would have spit in her
face, would she not be in abeyance for seven days? So a
minimum state, right, that's actually a very nice proof because God says
to Moses, you know, we can't sort of, you know, there's got
to be some minimum amount that's appropriate for this sort of state
of being censured, and that would be minimally seven days. So there
you have that idea that that's a minimum amount if somebody is
of a, you know, of a
duration for this state of being censured. Again the גמרא Gemara doesn't
explain what the practices of נזיפה Nezifah are, might have been the
same, might have been different. אמר רב חסדא נידוי שלנו כנזיפה שלהן.
Amar Rav Chisda Nidui She-lanu Ke-nezifah She-lahen. Our נידוי Nidui in בבל
Bavel is like their נזיפה Nezifah in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, which
presumably means it's our standard נידוי Nidui is of a shorter period
than theirs, which is fascinating. Why was that? Was it that they
had less of a sort of, you know, maybe for some reason
they had adopted a less harsh approach? Maybe they had certain like
a type of a less sense of, you know, political control or,
you know, authority, you know, they were less controlling, it was more
in בבל, Bavel, maybe more influenced by sort of the secular societies
and its institutions? So the actual, you know, in different like if
you think about the difference of, of in later times of אשכנזי
Ashkenazi communities and ספרדי Sephardi communities, right, אשכנזי Ashkenazi communities were more
cloistered and the rabbinic authority by and large I think was, I'm
speaking here only with a very limited amount of knowledge so if
there's any good medieval historians please correct me, but anyway, but you
know, because it was less cosmopolitan, was more cloistered and the sort
of the authority of the rabbinic authority in those communities was stronger
than in ספרדי Sephardi communities which was more integrated and assimilated and
more cosmopolitan. And maybe there was a similar type of a reality.
And by the way,
אשכנזי Ashkenazi culture comes more from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and ספרדי
Sephardi culture more from בבל. Bavel. So it's interesting to think why
was it that the, that these, that these things were less harsh
in בבל Bavel fundamentally of a shorter duration in בבל Bavel than
they were in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara continues.
ונזיפה דידהו שבעה. Ve-nezifah didhu shiva. So the גמרא Gemara says ונזיפה
דידהו שבעה ותו לא, Ve-nezifah didhu shiva ve-tu lo, and is their
נזיפה Nezifah only seven days and no more? והא רב שמעון ברבי
ובר קפרא הוו יתבי, Ve-ha Rav Shimon Berabbi u-Bar Kappara havu yatvei,
רב שמעון Rav Shimon the son of רבי Rabbi and בר קפרא
Bar Kappara were sitting. וקא גרסי, Ve-ka garsei, and they were learning.
וקשיא להו שמעתא, Ve-kashya le-hu shemat'ta, and they had a שמעתא shemat'ta
that was difficult to them.
אמר ליה רב שמעון לבר קפרא, Amar leh Rav Shimon le-Bar Kappara,
רב שמעון Rav Shimon רבי's Rabbi son said to בר קפרא, Bar
Kappara, דבר זה צריך רבי, Davar zeh tzarich Rabbi, this thing needs
a רבי, Rabbi, either needs a rabbi, a greater rabbi or needs
my father, needs רבי, Rabbi, but this is a real hard... but
presumably meant his father as we'll see. This is a really difficult
סוגיא, Sugya, if only רבי Rabbi were here. It's interesting calls his
father by not exactly his father's first name, his name was יהודה,
Yehuda, okay, but we call him רבי, Rabbi, okay, one minute. אמר
ליה בר קפרא לרב שמעון, Amar leh Bar Kappara le-Rav Shimon, and
בר קפרא Bar Kappara said back to רב שמעון, Rav Shimon, ומה
רבי אומר בדבר זה, U-mah Rabbi omer be-davar zeh, what can רבי
Rabbi tell us about this סוגיא? Sugya? Like this סוגיא Sugya is
impossible, רבי Rabbi couldn't help us with it. You know there's if
you look at the, if you look at the רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu
Gershom says אין רבי שבעולם שיבין דבר זה, Ein Rabbi she-ba-olam she-yavin
davar zeh, no there's no rabbi that could understand this, it's too
difficult on the סוגיא. Sugya. אזל אמר ליה לאבוה, Azal amar leh
le-avuh, so he went and he told his father what was happening.
רש״י Rashi the רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says he wasn't like telling
on him he was just talking to him, oh what did you
guys learn today? So anyway he told him over the story. איקפיד,
Ikpeid, so רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi was offended. אתא בר
קפרא לאיתחזויי ליה, Ata Bar Kappara le-itchazuyei leh, so בר קפרא Bar
Kappara came to appear before רבי Rabbi at one time, you know,
just to, maybe רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says that maybe רבי Rabbi
was sick and he came to visit him. אמר ליה בר קפרא
איני מכירך, Amar leh Bar Kappara eini makircha, so רבי Rabbi said,
בר קפרא Bar Kappara I don't know who you are. I mean
just called him בר קפרא, Bar Kappara, but okay anyway. I don't
recognize you. He refused to give him
any countenance. So מעולם. me'olam. I don't know who you are from,
I never knew who you were. Okay. ידע דנקיט מילתא בדעתיה. Yada
d'nakit milta b'da'atei. So בר קפרא Bar Kappara realized that
רבי Rebbe was upset about him over this issue.
And נהג נזיפותא בנפשיה תלתין יומין. nahag nezifuta b'nafshei tlatin yomin. And
he practiced on himself a sense of censure for thirty days. Now
what's fascinating about this is we have putting yourself in this state,
and we're going to find that that not only is true by
נזיפה, nezifa, we're going to see a later story that that's true
about נידוי nidui as well, that you can actually put yourself in
that state. And it was for thirty days, which after indicates that
the difference between נזיפה nezifa and נידוי nidui is not just duration,
because נידוי nidui is also thirty days. So it actually does make
it sound that there's difference in terms of the practice of נזיפה,
nezifa, but the גמרא Gemara never spells out what those practices are.
So there is some type of a lesser, the same way the
difference between נידוי nidui and חרם cherem is in intensity of the
practices, presumably there's a lesser, something that's less than נידוי nidui that's
even less severe practices called נזיפה, nezifa, we just don't know what
that set of practices are. Anyway, he did it for thirty days.
שוב פעם אחת, Shuv pa'am achat, another time, גזר רבי gazar Rebbe
שלא ישנו תלמידים בשוק. shelo yishnu talmidim bashuk. רבי Rebbe made a
גזירה gzera that the students should not be learning Torah out in
the marketplace, it's not respectful of Torah in the middle of the
שוק. shuk. So מאי דריש? Mai darish? Now we're going to see
it's not just because like maybe
there's business and it's smelly and those types of things, no, there's
also a specific aspect of it being too public. מאי דריש? Mai
darish? חמוקי ירכיך, Chamukei yerachayich, a פסוק pasuk by שיר השירים Shir
Hashirim often read in context of Torah,
the sort
of כמו חלאים. k'mo chalaim. So the
חמוקי chamukei I think is like the cleaving of your thighs is
like these very, a jewelry, how does it translate in English? Hidden?
Yeah, okay, anyway. So מה ירך בסתר, ma yarech b'seter, so the
same way a thigh is in private, people don't see it, אף
דברי תורה בסתר, af divrei Torah b'seter,
so Torah, because he understands, it's the Torah's the sort of משל
mashal here, or the נמשל, nimshal, Torah has to be in private
and it's not appropriate to do it in public in front of
people that don't appreciate it or whatever. Anyway, there's a certain obviously
a little bit of elitism there as well, it's something you keep
private.
There's other aspects of the גמרא Gemara there about that sense of
intimacy also, the very sort of sexual
or male-female metaphors that are used in terms of the learning of
תורה Torah and therefore it's something because of that intimacy that should
be done in private, of your way of connecting to the תורה.
Torah. So anyways, interesting sort of what types of issues values inform
this. So יצא רבי חייא ושנה לשני בני אחיו בשוק. Yatza Rabbi
Chiyya v'shanah lishnei bnei achiv bashuk. But רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya went
out and he was giving a שיעור shiur to his two nephews
in the marketplace, לרב ולרבה בר בר חנה, l'Rav u'l'Rabbah bar bar
Chana, to Rav and Rabbah bar bar Chana. שמע רבי איקפיד. Shama
Rebbe ikpid. רבי Rebbe heard and he got upset, he was offensive.
אתא רבי חייא לאיחזויי ליה. Ata Rabbi Chiyya l'ichzuyei leh. רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiyya came to appear before רבי. Rebbe. אמר ליה Amar leh
and he said to him, עייא, Iyya, since instead of calling him
חייא Chiyya he called him עייא Iyya like he mocked his name,
מי קורא לך בחוץ? Mi kore l'cha bachutz? I think somebody's calling
you outside, I think you're wanted outside. So he basically was a
same way of saying like I refuse to recognize you, except he
was closer to רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya so it was a little
bit.
He was learning בחוץ? bachutz?
Oh, that's a good point too, that's a good point. But also
it was a little bit more respectful, it's not like he completely
refused to recognize him, but it was a similar sense of I
think you're wanted, but good point about the בחוץ. bachutz. So ידע
דנקיט מילתא בדעתיה. Yada d'nakit milta b'da'atei. He knew, he realized that
רבי Rebbe was upset about him. So נהג נזיפותא בנפשיה תלתין יומין.
nahag nezifuta b'nafshei tlatin yomin. And he practiced this state of נזיבותא?
nezivuta? נזיפותא nezifuta for thirty days. ביום תלתין שלח ליה. Byom tlatin
shalach leh. On day thirty רבי Rebbe called for him, tells him
to come back. תו הדר שלח ליה דלא ליתי. Tu hadar shalach
leh d'lo leitei. Then רבי Rebbe sent another messenger that told him
don't come back on day thirty. מעיקרא מאי סבר ולבסוף מאי סבר?
Me'ikara mai savar u'l'vasof mai savar? So the גמרא Gemara is saying
and what did רבי Rebbe think initially that he beckoned him on
day thirty and what was he thinking when he reversed that? So
מעיקרא סבר מקצת היום ככולו. Me'ikara savar miktzat hayom k'kulo. Originally he
thought, so here's the question, how do you measure the days, like
the question of אבילות, aveilus, and again an interesting comparison to אבילות.
aveilus. Is the day seven and day thirty, does it end in
the beginning of day seven or does it end only after the
end of day seven? Does it end in the beginning of day
thirty or only at the end of day thirty? So we have
a principle of מקצת היום ככולו, miktzat hayom k'kulo, that once you
begin the day,
that sort of is a little bit in the beginning is enough.
So he figured okay, it's already the middle of day thirty, he
can come, מקצת היום ככולו. miktzat hayom k'kulo. ולבסוף סבר לא אמרינן
מקצת היום ככולו. U'l'vasof savar lo amrinan miktzat hayom k'kulo. In the
end he decided we don't say that, maybe we don't say it
in general, we don't say it by נזיפה? nezifa? By נזיפותא. nezifuta.
Anyway, so he reversed himself. ולסוף אתא. U'l'sof ata. But anyway רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiyya came that day. So אמר ליה, Amar leh, so
רבי Rebbe said to him, אמאי אתית? Amai atit? Why did you
come?
אמר ליה, Amar leh, דשלחת לי. D'shalacht li. Because you called me.
אמר ליה, Amar leh, דלא ליתי. D'lo leitei. I told you not
to come. So Rabbi said back to him, "והא שלחי לך דלא
תיתי, veha shalchi lach delo teiti, but then I sent afterwards to
say don't come." אמר ליה, Amar leih, "דא חזיתי ודא לא חזיתי,
da chaziti veda lo chaziti, I got the first message, I didn't
get the second message." So קרי עליה, kari aleih, so Rabbi said
about him the verse, ברצות ה' דרכי איש, Birtzot Hashem darchai ish,
when God desires the paths of man, so גם אויביו ישלים לו,
gam oyvav yashlim lo, even his enemies will make peace with him.
So obviously, you know, it was through God. Here we were, we
were a little bit at war, we were opposing one another, we,
you know, God made it that there was השגחה פרטית hashgacha pratit
here, made it that you didn't hear the second message, we make
peace today rather than tomorrow. Okay, so מאי טעמא אמרת לה הכי?
mai ta'ama amart lah hachi? So then Rabbi said, "And now that
there's thirty, you know, you appropriately did this to yourself to show
that you acted inappropriately, but now at least let's talk about it.
Why did you do this? Why did you go against my ruling?"
So אמר ליה amar leih דכתיב dechtiv because the verse says חכמות
בחוץ תרונה, Chachmot bachutz taronah, that wisdom should, you know, sing out
in the, you know, in the outside, it should be public. We
should, you know, we should do it in public. Everybody should hear
about, should hear תורה. Torah. We shouldn't keep it more secluded. So
אמר ליה, amar leih, so Rabbi said back to him, "אם קרית
לא שנית, im karita lo shanita, if you learned מקרא, Mikra, you
did not learn enough משנה. Mishnah. ואם שנית לא שלשת, Ve'im shanita
lo shilashta, I'm sorry, you didn't do it twice. ואם שנית לא
שלשת, Ve'im shanita lo shilashta, and if you did it twice,
ואם שלשת לא פירשו לך, ve'im shilashta lo pirshu lach, they didn't
explain it to you." So, you know, it's very nice to quote
a פסוק, pasuk, but you don't really understand. Why? חכמות בחוץ תרונה.
Chachmot bachutz taronah. What does it mean wisdom will sing in the
market, in the outside? So כרבא, kerava, like Rava, who was a
few generations after Rabbi. So obviously this is a little, you know,
anachronistic. But okay. דאמר רבא De'amar Rava because Rava says כל העוסק
בתורה מבפנים תורתו מכרזת עליו מבחוץ. kol ha'osek baTorah mibifnim Torato machrezet
alav mibachutz. It doesn't mean you go and you proclaim your תורה
Torah outdoors and you teach your תורה Torah in public. It means
that if you learn your תורה Torah in private, like I, Rabbi,
am saying you're supposed to learn your תורה, Torah, but nevertheless it
will sort of, you know, the wisdom will announce itself. Not that
you talk the תורה, Torah, you know, out in public, but your
own, you know, sort of religious and intellectual, you know, sort of
higher level that you've accomplished will be obvious to everyone. הגמרא haGemara
says, "והא כתיב, veha ktiv, but doesn't the verse say לא מראש
בסתר דברתי?" lo merosh beseter dibarti? I did not speak initially in
private, like maybe referring to מתן תורה, Matan Torah, but presumably held
up as a model that תורה Torah is not something that's supposed
to be kept
private. אהו ביומי דכלה, Ahu beyomei dechalla, that's in the days of
the כלה, kalla, you know, when everybody gathers before the ימים טובים
yamim tovim to have a big שיעור shiur in public. Okay, there
are some days that you give a public lecture, but it doesn't
mean that you're always talking about this in public. Now again, it
might be hard for people to understand what this is about, what
this elitism is about. You know, I will remind you nowadays that
here, you know, everybody is using Artscroll גמרא Gemara and all this
type of thing. You know, there were like major fights going back
a hundred years about whether, about translating the תלמוד. Talmud. You know,
because it just makes this more obscure learning, and, you know, that
requires a lot of training to really understand it, available to a
wide public that is not sufficient, doesn't have the sufficient background, isn't
sufficiently trained, and might, you know, come to misunderstandings of it, and,
you know, so there's a real and now of course everybody takes
it for granted like, duh, so it was without a question and
look at the amazing thing Artscroll does, it spread, you know, these
other translations have done, and all these things, and now, you know,
it's תורה Torah accessible to all. But there was a real sense
like, you know, like, you know, a little knowledge is a dangerous
thing and people that, you know, will misuse it and misunderstand it
and it really should be treated to people who are trained and
can handle it. So there really have always been these two sort
of competing types of approaches. Yeah, Michael?
What was it before? It's very interesting that Rabbi is getting caught
up in the, I guess, the minutiae of whether I can do
it the last day or not. I mean, we also learned that
whoever
institutes a ban can revoke it, right? And he could revoke it
any time he wanted, even on the last day.
Yeah, but he didn't want to. Right. All right. Yeah, Charlie?
The question was on Hus like that at the end of the
Middle Ages and early modern times about whether it was okay to
translate it and the general opinion of the church leadership was no.
Right. Well, it is true, on the one hand, right, the חז"ל
Chazal and rabbinic approach to this has always been very different than
the church approach. You know, the church has always been very much
about controlling access to the Bible and, you know, and not translating
it and only the, you know, and only the, you know, and
only the religious authorities are the ones that actually are, you know,
are literate and actually have access to this. Whereas, you know, in
חז"ל, Chazal, you know, they talk about obviously the institutions of קריאת
התורה Kriyat HaTorah and everybody knowing תורה Torah and the famous story
about actually, it just occurs to me that Rabbi Chiya is the
one, the famous גמרא Gemara about גדולי מעשי חייא Gedolei Ma'asei Chiya
where Rabbi Chiya went and he basically, you know, there's stories about
how he went to all these different villages and got everybody to
sort of like, you know, wrote ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah and got
everybody to learn תורה Torah and to teach תורה Torah to one
another and so on and to create this very widespread, it's the
same Rabbi Chiya, knowledge of תורה Torah and creating essentially the גמרא
Gemara is about up... essentially a public school system, so there's definitely
was a desire that everybody have access at least to מקרא, Mikra,
okay, which is fascinating, you know, that's like direct דבר השם, Devar
Hashem, that's exactly what the church was sort of protecting access to.
Okay, that actually was something, what, the
rabbis were also against translation of מקרא. Mikra.
Right, but that might have been more about the concern about like
the non-Jews, because they were very in favor of the Aramaic translation,
right? And the תרגום Targum was a regular part of קריאת התורה.
Kriyat HaTorah. So access to מקרא Mikra and understanding מקרא, Mikra, they
were very much opposite of what the church approach was. But access
to like גמרא, Gemara, that type of level of learning, that seems
to have been more protected. It's actually interesting in that context that
part of their whole debate here about whether to teach גמרא Gemara
in public or what not is based on a discussion of פסוקים
Psukim and whether you really understand פסוקים. Psukim. So I'm sure there's
more to figure out about that.
Yes, I actually that was my original question. We're looking at that
difficult
סוגיא, Sugya, right, the יתבי
וגרסי.
Yatvei
VeGarsei. גרסי Garsei usually means to read.
No, גרסי... Garsei...
yeah, but it's in the context
of an oral conversation, right? There was no text in front of
them.
Yeah, but no. They're learning... it's true that a גרסא Girsa we
say now means a text, but לגרוס Ligros is like also like
to grind wheat and it's, you know, the whole wheat metaphor, מרי
דחטי Marei DeChitei and so on and גרסי Garsei is very much
about the about like the oral tradition.
So when they had that difficult סוגיא Sugya no rabbi could come
over and דרשן darshen the סוגיא, Sugya, but nonetheless it was nothing
in in between.
Right, yeah, but they were trying to figure out I don't know
some difficult משניות Mishnayot in עוקצין Okatzin or something, you know? Right.
Everything they knew, it was all oral.
Right. Okay, we're going to move on. Okay, so we had go
ahead, yeah, go ahead.
Rabbi Chiya compiled the תוספתא, Tosefta, right, which itself was a bit
of a challenge to רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi's authority of
in his משנה. Mishnah.
Right, although that gets into more complicated questions of the relationship of
תוספתא Tosefta and משנה. Mishnah. But okay, let's keep on. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: Anyway, you have all these stories that
said it was thirty days, so not seven days. So the גמרא
Gemara says, רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, let's just sort of end this
debate, רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, היי חמוקי ירכיך מאי עביד ליה? Hai
Chamekei Yerechaichi Mai Avid Leh? What does he do with this verse
about sort of the, you know, the the thigh and the hidden
thigh? So מוקי לה בצדקה וגמילות חסדים. Muki Leh Bitzdakah U'gemilut Chasadim.
No, to acts of צדקה, tzedakah, your acts of גמילות חסדים, gemilut
chasadim, that should be kept in private. You don't go around a)
for the respect of the person you're giving to and b) for
your own sense, you don't go around boasting oh look what a
בעל צדקה ba'al tzedakah I am. That's something that you do בצניעות.
bitzniut. But תורה Torah is something that should be spread and should
be in public. Anyway says the גמרא Gemara says: אלמא נזיפה דידהו
תלתין יומי? Almana Nezifa Dilhu Telatin Yomei? You see their נזיפה nezifa
is thirty days. So the גמרא Gemara says no, נזיפה דנשיא שאני.
nezifa d'nasi shani. The נזיפה nezifa of a נשיא nasi of רבי
יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi, that has a different weight. Now of
course רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi wasn't the one who put
them in נזיפה. nezifa. They did נזיפה nezifa on themselves. Okay, but
it was as a result of being censured. So the actual practice
was something they imposed, but in essence they got if you want
to use the metaphor the גמרא Gemara earlier, they got spat in
the face on by רבי. Rebbe. And then they just adopted the
practice of the נזיפה. nezifa. Again, it's fascinating we don't know exactly
what that practice is. Okay, so maybe by the way, maybe all
נזיפה nezifa means is not to appear in front of the person
you offended. Right, in both of those cases רבי Rebbe was just
basically saying get out of here, I don't want to I don't
want to have anything to do with you. You know, and in
the מרים Miriam case מרים Miriam is מחוץ למחנה. michutz l'machaneh. So
I don't know. The גמרא Gemara never spells out what the practices
are, but maybe it is just exactly this. If you've been censured
then you don't appear in front of that person for a period
of time. Okay, we don't see anything more about what that practice
means. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ונזיפה דידן,
Ve'nezifa Didan, so our נידוי nidduy is for seven days, is the
same duration as their נזיפה. nezifa. And our נזיפה, nezifa, כמה הוי?
kama havei? How long would that be? That would be חד יומא.
chad yoma. That would just be one day. So everything is less
for us in בבל Bavel than in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. כי
הא דשמואל ומר עוקבא, Ki Ha De'shmuel U'Mar Ukva, like the story
of שמואל Shmuel and מר עוקבא, Mar Ukva, כי הוו יתבי ki
havi yasvei when they were sitting גרסי שמעתא garsei shmaita and they
again they were learning a סוגיא, sugya, הוו יתבי מר עוקבא קמיה
דשמואל, havi yasvei Mar Ukva k'mei de'Shmuel, so מר עוקבא Mar Ukva
was sitting in front of שמואל, Shmuel, בריחוק ארבע אמות, berichuk arba
amos, four אמות amos away, because to show respect that שמואל Shmuel
was the greater תורה Torah authority, so he didn't... בריחוק ארבע אמות
berichuk arba amos is also what you don't sit within ארבע אמות
arba amos of somebody who's in נידוי. nidduy. So fascinating parallels that
are going on here, but anyway here was a show of respect,
you're not so you're not so pals-y with him, he's the bigger
rabbinic תורה Torah authority. But כי הוו יתבי בדינא ki havi yasvei
bedina when they sat in דין, din, הוו יתבי שמואל קמיה דמר
עוקבא havi yasvi Shmuel k'mei de'Mar Ukva then the relationship was reversed.
שמואל Shmuel was in the presence of מר עוקבא, Mar Ukva, מר
עוקבא Mar Ukva was the authority, שמואל Shmuel was in a secondary
role, and בריחוק ארבע אמות berichuk arba amos and שמואל Shmuel was
four אמות amos away from him. So their you know distance is
relative, they're always four אמות amos away from one another, but the
question is who is viewed of as sitting in front of who?
Okay, so מר עוקבא Mar Ukva was the greater if you would
sort of like political authority and therefore when they were in דין,
din, which also had to do you know with like sort of
political power, שמואל Shmuel was מר עוקבא Mar Ukva was the greater
authority. When it was in תורה Torah שמואל Shmuel was the greater
authority. Okay, so now and as... רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom points out
מר עוקבא Mar Ukva was actually the נשיא, Nasi, although I don't
know about נשיא, Nasi, he was in בבל, Bavel, but anyway, okay,
some type of parallel position. Okay. What? ריש גלותא. Reish Galusa. I
know, but he says נשיא. Nasi. רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says נשיא.
Nasi. Anyway, okay, so that's what they were doing. והוה חייכי ליה
דוכתא למר עוקבא בציפתא, Vahavei chaichei lei douchta leMar Ukva betzifta,
they would basically like lay out a, you know, sort of a
place for מר עוקבא Mar Ukva with like a mat, ויתיב עלויה,
Veyasiv alvayei, and he would sit on it, כי היכי דלישתמען מיליה,
Ki heichi delishtaman milei, in order that his words could be heard.
What does that mean?
So,
so, ki... I'm sorry, כי היכי דלישתמען מיליה, Ki heichi delishtaman milei,
that in order, I'm sorry, that he would hear what שמואל Shmuel
had to say, that even though somehow, yeah, I'm trying to think
exactly figure out what this... what? Somehow the acoustics, somehow even though
מר עוקבא Mar Ukva was the one that was sitting higher in
the sense of the court, he wanted to make sure that he
heard what שמואל Shmuel was saying because obviously he could even in
the court context he wanted to be hearing שמואל Shmuel and learning
from שמואל. Shmuel. But I don't get the exact choreography here. Anyway,
כל יומא הוה מלווי ליה מר עוקבא לשמואל עד אושפיזיה. Kol yoma
hava malvei lei Mar Ukva leShmuel ad ushpiziei.
Every day מר עוקבא Mar Ukva would accompany שמואל Shmuel until שמואל's
Shmuel's lodging place, you know, again, that מר עוקבא Mar Ukva would,
even though מר עוקבא Mar Ukva again was the, you know, נשיא,
Nasi, the greater political authority, he would always be doing these signs
of respect to שמואל. Shmuel. So even in the דין, din, though
he sat with... clearly so that he could hear what שמואל Shmuel
said, he would accompany שמואל Shmuel to שמואל's Shmuel's lodging place. יומא
חד איטריד בדיניה. Yoma chad itrid bidinei. One day מר עוקבא Mar
Ukva was very, you know, preoccupied by the court case he was
dealing with, and he didn't... he wasn't realizing that he had forgotten
to accompany שמואל, Shmuel, and he was doing... he was on his...
you know, on his own channel, and then he... he went home
to his own lodging place, והוה אזיל שמואל בתריה. Vahavei azil Shmuel
basrei. And therefore שמואל Shmuel sort of said, okay, מר עוקבא's Mar
Ukva's not following me, let me accompany מר עוקבא Mar Ukva to
where מר עוקבא Mar Ukva was going. כי מטו לביתיה, Ki matu
lebeiseih, so when they came to מר עוקבא's Mar Ukva's house, אמר
ליה, Amar lei, לא נגה ליה למר למישרי לי בתגרא? Lo naga
lei lemar lemishrei li betigra?
So, isn't it...
like isn't it... like... isn't it enough that I've followed you, למישרי
לי מר בתגרא, lemishrei li mar betigra, like you know, give me
permission to return. Meaning, like there he was, you know, you've got
to imagine מר עוקבא's Mar Ukva's head was in the clouds, he
was walking home, didn't realize A, didn't realize he was supposed to
have first walked שמואל Shmuel home, he was being followed by שמואל,
Shmuel, מר עוקבא Mar Ukva then got into the house and he
didn't realize that שמואל Shmuel was still there and waiting around, like
מר עוקבא Mar Ukva was completely somewhere else. So then שמואל Shmuel
said to him, isn't it enough that I've accompanied you this far,
can I please go? Like he didn't even give him a recognition
or leave, okay? ידע דנקט מילתא בדעתיה, Yada denakat milsa bedataih, and
מר עוקבא Mar Ukva realized that שמואל Shmuel was a little bit
annoyed at him, you know, was angry at him. So נהג נזיפותא
בנפשיה. Nahag nezifusa benafshaih. So now look at this, שמואל, Shmuel, מר
עוקבא, Mar Ukva, who here is in the Rebbe position, in the
sense of being the נשיא, Nasi, but this often is sort of,
you know, the thing that gets like inverted in the בבלי, Bavli,
is that the role of the political role of נשיא Nasi or
ריש גלותא, Reish Galusa, whatever, is obviously does not have weight, it's
all the Torah status. So here שמואל... Shmuel... you know, מר עוקבא
Mar Ukva who has the greater political authority, he's the one that
has offended the greater Torah authority, שמואל, Shmuel, and he's practicing נזיפותא
nezifusa on himself. So נהג נזיפותא בנפשיה חד יומא, Nahag nezifusa benafshaih
chad yoma, one day. So that's the idea that in בבל, Bavel,
נזיפותא nezifusa is one day. Okay. ההיא איתתא דהוה יתבא בשבילא, Hahi
itesa dahava yasva bishvila, so there was a certain woman, that's the
end of that story. So that's the concept is נזיפותא nezifusa and
the difference between בבל Bavel and ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Now another
story. ההיא איתתא דהוה יתבא בשבילא, Hahi itesa dahava yasva bishvila, there
was a woman sitting in... on the path, הוה פשטה כרעא, Hava
pashta kara, her legs were stretched out, והוה מנפשיה, Vahavei menafsheia, and
she was like sifting wheat or something, so... שערי, sharei, or like
barley, she was sifting barley. והוה
חליף ואזיל, Vahavei chalif ve’azil, צורבא מרבנן, tzurba merabbanan, one of the
rabbis of the academy was walking by, ולא איקנא מקמיה, Velo ikna
mikamei,
and she was not, you know, humbled in his presence, which might
mean that she didn't show him respect, might mean also that he
found it, you know, disrespectful that she was sitting there with her
legs maybe exposed or stretched out. So אמר, Amar, he said, כמה
חציפא
היא איתתא, Kama chatzipa hi itesa, how, you know,
how... how much... how... how-dik is this woman. That's the official translation
of חציפא. chatzipa. How-dik is this woman. אתאי לקמיה דרב נחמן, Asai
lekamei deRav Nachman, so...
so she came to רב נחמן Rav Nachman because she said, look,
he publicly offended me, you know. Interesting, so she's now the one
that's been offended. אמר לה, Amar lah, מי שמעת שמתא מפומיה? Mi
shamas shamta mipumei?
Did you hear him actually utter a שמתא, shamta, נידוי, nidui, did
he put you in נידוי? nidui? אמרה ליה לא, Amra lei lo,
so... she said no, he didn't actually say... say that I was
put in חרם, cherem, a נידוי. nidui. אמר לה, Amar lah, זילי
נהוג נזיפותא חד יומא בנפשך, Zili nehoug nezifusa chad yoma benafshach, so
he said to her, go and practice נזיפותא nezifusa for one day
on yourself. If he didn't put you in נידוי, nidui, he only
expressed his offense and displeasure, you know, it's the again here the
metaphorical spitting in the face, then that translates into a practice of
נזיפות nezifus and go do it for one day. So apparently she
was appearing not to complain, she was appearing to know, how should
I practice? This rabbi censured me in public, what is my proper
way of practicing? And he said, okay it was a censure, it
wasn't נידוי, nidui, so that you do a practice for one day.
So in all these cases what's fascinating is, is that you never
have the rabbi although the rabbi issues a נידוי, nidui, you never
have the rabbi issuing a נזיפות. nezifus. A נזיפות nezifus is something
that you realize by the way somebody has reacted to you that
you're being you've offended that person and you're being censured by a
rabbi and therefore it's a way it's a practice that you implicitly
understand now how you're supposed to practice in response. Okay, so that
seems all of these cases that's sort of what the reality of
this נזיפות nezifus is. It doesn't have the formal issuing, it's sort
of your awareness of your sense of censure and then your response
to that. Again, what that actually means in practice might just be
not appearing before the person, not exactly clear what that practice means.
Okay. Okay,
זוטרא בר טוביה הוה קפסיק סידרא קמיה דרב יהודה. Zutra bar Tuvia
hava kapasek sidra kamei d'Rav Yehuda. So זוטרא בר טוביה Zutra bar
Tuvia was teaching like the פרשיות, parshiyot, the פסוקים, pesukim, in front
of רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. כי מטא להאי פסוקא ki mata l'hai
pasuka when he got to the following verse: ואלה דברי דוד האחרונים,
ve-eleh divrei David ha-achronim, these are the words, these are the final
words of David. אמר ליה amar leh he said to him: אחרונים
מכלל דאיכא ראשונים ראשונים מאי נינהו? achronim mikhlal d'ika rishonim rishonim mai
ninhu? So it says the last words, it suggests that there are
earlier words, where are the earlier words? Now obviously David had said
earlier sayings, but the words of דברי divrei where it has the
word of דבר, davar, using specifically that, and as רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu
Gershom points out דברי divrei means נבואה, nevuah, so that is the
only time it says דברי דוד. divrei David. So where does it
ever earlier say earlier דברי דוד, divrei David, that particular
phrase? שתיק ולא אמר ליה ולא מידי, shasik velo amar leh velo
midi, he refused to respond. It's quite fascinating. Here's the guy learning
the פסוקים, pesukim, he's asking the greater rabbinic
authority רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda refuses to
respond. הדר אמר ליה, hadar amar leh, so he figured if he
didn't answer the first time I'll ask again. אחרונים מכלל דאיכא ראשונים
ראשונים מאי היא? achronim mikhlal d'ika rishonim rishonim mai hi? So he
asked him again.
שתיק, shasik, sorry did I skip a line? אחרונים מכלל דאיכא ראשונים
ראשונים מאי היא? achronim mikhlal d'ika rishonim rishonim mai hi? אמר ליה
amar leh he said to him: מה דעתך דלא ידע פירושא דהאי
קרא? ma da'atach d'lo yada perusha d'hai kra?
So what do you think? You think that I don't know the
meaning of this verse?
לאו
גברא רבא הוא? lav gavra raba hu? Isn't he a great person?
Meaning what? You don't think you're asking me again, you don't think
I know? Aren't I a weighty authority? Aren't I a great rabbi?
So he's talking about himself in the third person. It's also fascinating
talking about himself in the third person so he's you know sort
of holding emphasizing the כבוד kavod that is due to him.
So ידע yada he knew דנקט מילתא בדעתיה, d'naqat milta beda'ateh, he
realized that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was angry at him. So נהג
נזיפותא בנפשיה חד יומא. nahag nezifuta benafsheh chad yoma. So he practiced
again this state of נזיפות nezifus for one day. Okay, so all
these stories are stories of one day. Quite fascinating, right? Sort of
like being hypersensitive to when a rabbi gets angry and offended at
you and says something to show he's displeased with you and that
you're supposed to pick up on that signal and practice, yeah, and
practice this status of נזיפות. nezifus.
It turns the whole thing, so all these stories also are the
person themselves not being formally put in this state.
Right, to themselves picking up on the signals, exactly.
But it also kind of overturns the whole political authority thing.
It's not imposed from above, it's
from below.
Right, that's true, and it heightens, so it's not as much of
that
bald exercise of power, it's more just sort of cultivating a sensitivity
towards the issue of right and coming from the person himself. Maybe
the אמוראים Amora'im are also commenting on themselves?
I mean, they're so touchy.
Yeah, well, that is, so you know that's a thing,
but they have so much power you don't have to be touchy.
Yeah, but you know, but I think that the point that Dov
makes also like if you can get people to internalize that sense
of respect and deference and be sensitive to, oh my God I
just offended my רבי rebbe in a way that's much more powerful
than having to use these more formal forms of כפייה, kefiyah, right?
These
exactly. So okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, ודאתינא להא, veda-atina l'ha,
now that we're talking about it, let's understand what the פסוק pasuk
means. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda didn't want to respond or he whatever
he was offended he was asked twice, but it was a good
question. אחרונים מכלל דאיכא ראשונים ראשונים מאי היא? achronim mikhlal d'ika rishonim
rishonim mai hi? So where does it earlier say דברי דוד? divrei
David? That particular phrase. So it says: וידבר דוד לה' את דברי
השירה הזאת. vayedaber David l'Hashem et divrei hashirah hazot. So it says
דברי השירה, divrei hashirah, doesn't say דברי דוד. divrei David. So it
says וידבר דברי השירה Vayidaber divrei hashirah ביום הציל אותו מכף כל
אויביו ומכף שאול. bayom hitzil oso mikaf kol oyvav umikaf Shaul. אמר
הקדוש ברוך הוא לדוד, Amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu l'David, God said to
דוד: David: דוד, David, שירה אתה אומר על מפלתו של שאול? shirah
atah omer al mapalaso shel Shaul?
You're saying a שירה shirah on the, on the, for the fall
of שאול? Shaul? אלמלא אתה שאול והוא דוד, ilmaleh atah Shaul vehu
David, had you been שאול Shaul
and he had the roles been reversed and he had been דוד,
David, אבדתי כמה דוד מפניו, ibadti kamah David mipanav, I would have
destroyed many דודס, Davids, you know, for his sake. So, you know,
which basically means
that I mean the way רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom at least says
it is, is that he was a greater, he, you know, don't
think you're so wonderful. He was actually more righteous than you. It's
just the way, you know, history played out and you're, you know,
and the, and sort of, and you know, the מזל mazal is
the way רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says, you know, various things led
to this, but don't make it think that you're so wonderful and
you're so great. היינו דכתיב, Hainu d'ksiv, that's what's meant by the
verse שגיון לדוד אשר שר לה', Shigayon l'David asher shar la-Shem, a
שגיון, shigayon,
which in the simple sense means obviously some sense, some type of
a song, but here it's understood as שגגה, shigagah, an error. על
דברי כוש בן ימיני, Al divrei Kush ben Yemini, for the sake,
on the matter of כוש Kush the son of ימיני. Yemini. So
who do we know is the ימיני, Yemini, is the בנימיני, Binyamini,
from בנימין, Binyamin, שאול. Shaul. So שאול Shaul here is identified as
כוש. Kush. So the גמרא Gemara says וכי כוש שמו ולא שאול
שמו? vechi Kush shemo v'lo Shaul shemo? אלא מה כושי משונה בעורו,
ela mah Kushi meshuneh b'oro, the same way a כושי, Kushi, an
Ethiopian, has a different
skin, אף שאול משונה במעשיו, af Shaul meshuneh b'maasav,
שאול Shaul was distinct here in a good way, like he was
exceptional in his deeds. כיוצא בדבר אתה אומר, Kayotzei badavar atah omer,
על אודות האשה הכושית אשר לקח, al odos ha'ishah ha-Kushis asher lakach,
by משה, Moshe, the כושית Kushis woman he took. וכי כושית שמה
ולא ציפורה שמה? V'chi Kushis shemah v'lo Tziporah shemah? It's funny, it
never said her name was כושית, Kushis, it says that he was
כושית, Kushis, but okay, anyway, isn't her name ציפורה? Tziporah? אלא מה
כושי משונה בעורו אף ציפורה משונה במעשיה, Ela mah Kushi meshuneh b'oro
af Tziporah meshuneh b'maaseha,
again meaning she was exceptional in her deeds.
רש"י Rashi says she was beautiful, here's it's her deeds.
Yeah, yeah, right, רש"י Rashi on the תורה, Torah, right. כיוצא בדבר
אתה אומר, Kayotzei badavar atah omer, וישמע עבד מלך הכושי. vayishma Eved
Melech ha-Kushi. וכי כושי שמו ולא צדקיהו שמו? V'chi Kushi shemo v'lo
Tzidkiyahu shemo? About a פסוק pasuk in ירמיהו Yirmiyahu
referring to צדקיהו. Tzidkiyahu. אלא מה כושי משונה בעורו אף צדקיהו משונה
במעשיו. Ela mah Kushi meshuneh b'oro af Tzidkiyahu meshuneh b'maasav. צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu
was exceptional
in his deeds, although questionable here exactly how that's supposed to be
understood. כיוצא בדבר אתה אומר, Kayotzei badavar atah omer, הלוא כבני כושיים
אתם לי בני ישראל. halo kivnei Kushiyim atem li b'nei Yisrael. וכי
כושיים שמם ולא ישראל שמם? V'chi Kushiyim shemam v'lo Yisrael shemam? אלא,
ela, and here actually the תורה Torah is explicit, it's making a,
an analogy. You are like the בני כושיים. b'nei Kushiyim. אלא מה
כושי משונה בעורו אף ישראל משונים במעשיהם מכל האומות, ela mah Kushi
meshuneh b'oro af Yisrael meshunim b'maaseihem mikol ha'umos, which can sometimes be
a compliment and sometimes an insult, but okay, depending on what the
context is. But anyway, here it's all being read as a question
as exceptional. Anyway, so there, and presumably what the גמרא Gemara didn't
spell out, but presumably on the word of שגיון shigayon as the
word of שגגה, shigagah, that דוד David recognized his error and because
he recognized how exceptional שאול Shaul was. אמר שמואל בר נחמני אמר
רבי יונתן, Amar Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonasan, מה דכתיב, mai
d'ksiv, what's meant by the verse, now that we're talking about דוד,
David, נאום דוד בן ישי ונאום הגבר הוקם על. Neum David ben
Yishai u-neum hagever hukam al. Says דוד David the son of ישי,
Yishai, says the man who was raised up above. נאום דוד בן
ישי שהקים עולה, Neum David ben Yishai she-hekim olah, the word על
al means עולה, olah, the yoke, של תשובה, shel teshuvah, the yoke
of תשובה, teshuvah, that by the whole story of בת שבע Bas
Sheva and so on he demonstrated to the world the process of
תשובה. teshuvah.
And רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom quotes the גמרא Gemara in עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah that says לא דוד ראוי לאותו מעשה אלא כדי להורות
תשובה ליחיד, lo David rauy l'oso maaseh ela k'dei l'horos teshuvah l'yachid,
or אומרים לו לך אצל דוד, omrim lo leich eitzel David, that
דוד David really was not at a level that he should have
sinned with בת שבע, Bas Sheva, but in the end it happened
as a, so it serves as a lesson for everybody else, which
is an interesting parallel to the story of שאול. Shaul. You know,
what happened to שאול, Shaul, you know, is not necessarily reflective of
שאול's Shaul's righteousness and don't, you know. So here what happened to
דוד David is not necessarily reflective of דוד's David's righteousness or lack
thereof.
אמר אלוהי ישראל לי דיבר צור ישראל מושל באדם צדיק. Amar Elohei
Yisrael li diber tzur Yisrael moshel ba'adam tzaddik.
I'm sorry, I
didn't get this פסוק pasuk correctly. מושל יראת אלוהים. moshel yiras Elokim.
I'm sorry, what?
It ends מושל יראת
אלוהים.
moshel
yiras Elokim.
Okay, מושל יראת אלוהים. moshel yiras Elokim. Sorry, thank you. So I
was, okay. So says the God of Israel, to me is a
matter, the rock of Israel who rules over the man, the צדיק
tzaddik is, the righteous person
מושל יראת אלוהים moshel yiras Elokim rules over the fear of God
or the fear of God rules over him. A little hard the
grammar of this verse, and now we'll see what the גמרא Gemara
is going to do with it. מאי קאמר? Mai ka'amar? What's this
verse say? אמר רבי אבהו הכי קאמר, Amar Rabbi Abbahu hachi ka'amar,
here's how to read it. אמר אלוהי ישראל לי דיבר צור ישראל
אני מושל באדם.
Amar Elohei Yisrael li
diber tzur Yisrael ani moshel ba'adam. So says the God of Israel
to me is a matter, says the rock of Israel, I rule
over the man, the human. מי מושל בי? Mi moshel bi? But
who rules over me? צדיק, tzaddik, the righteous person rules over me.
So צדיק מושל יראת אלוהים, tzaddik moshel yiras Elokim, sort of taking
out the word יראת, yiras, מושל. moshel. is מושל *moshel* over God.
שאני גוזר גזירה *she'ani gozer gezeirah*, I make a גזירה *gezeirah*, ומבטלה
*u'mevattelah*, and the צדיק *tzaddik* is מבטל *mevattel* it. Okay the famous
you know say on one hand some גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says צדיק
גוזר והקדוש ברוך הוא מקיים tzaddik gozer v'haKadosh Baruch Hu mikayem, *tzaddik
gozer v'Hakadosh Baruch Hu mikayeim*. This גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going even
further, you know הקדוש ברוך הוא גוזר וצדיק מבטלה *Hakadosh Baruch Hu
gozer v'tzaddik mevattelah*. So a צדיק *tzaddik* even has the power over
God to countermand God's rulings. אלה שמות הגבורים אשר לדוד *Eileh shemot
hagiborim asher l'David*, יושב בשבת *Yoshev baShevet*. These are the names of
the righteous people of דוד David *David* who are יושב בשבת *Yoshev
baShevet*. מאי קאמר *Mai ka'amar*? What does this mean? Like אמר Amar
רב rav אלעזר *Amar Rav Elazar*, אמר רבי Rebbe אבהו הכי קאמר
*Amar Rabbi Abbahu hachi ka'amar*: ואלו שמות גבורותיו של דוד David *V'eileh
shemot gevurotav shel David*, יושב בשבת *Yoshev baShevet*. So these are the
mighty deeds of דוד David *David* sitting בשבת *baShevet*. What does that
mean? So בשעה שהיה יושב בישיבה *B'sha'ah shehayah yoshev b'yeshivah*, לא יושב
על גבי כרים וכסתות *lo yoshev al gabi karim u'khastot*. When דוד
David *David* was sitting in the ישיבה *yeshivah*, like here's דוד David
*David* sort of learning תורה Torah, *Torah*, he would not sit on
mats and on pillows, אלא על גבי קרקע *ella al gabi karka*,
he would sit like right on the ground. וכל כמה דהוה רבי
Rebbe, עירא היאירי קיים *V'chol kamma dehavah Rebbi Ira haYa'iri kayyam*, as
long as his רבי Rebbe עירא היאירי *Rebbi Ira haYa'iri* was around,
הוה מתני להו לרבנן על גבי כרים וכסתות *havah matni lehu l'rabbanan
al gabi karim u'khastot*.
So רבי Rebbe עירא *Rebbi Ira* would, as a show of his
status, would teach the רבנן rabbanan *rabbanan*, right here we're having דוד
*David* and everybody there in a rabbinic study hall, would teach the
רבנן rabanan, *rabbanan* and רבי עירא *Rebbi Ira* was sitting on top
of these pillows. כי נח נפשיה Nach nafshieh *Ki nach nafsheih*, when
רבי עירא *Rebbi Ira* died, הוה מתני דוד לרבנן *havah matni David
l'rabbanan*. So דוד *David* then became the ראש ישיבה *Rosh Yeshivah*. I
mean by the way, it's fascinating, right, 'cause רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi
Yehuda haNasi *Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi* is understood to be a descendant of
דוד *David*. And there you have the combination of this idea of
political leadership and rabbinic leadership. So here it's sort of being projected
back onto דוד *David*. So now דוד *David* is the next ראש
ישיבה *Rosh Yeshivah*.
And he was the person who consolidated that model. Right? In the
תנ"ך *Tanakh*, right?
Well, a Torah leadership, and you didn't have the same of like
rabbinic... Religious leadership. Religious leadership. Right, but here it's specifically like Torah
leadership. So now דוד *David* is teaching the רבנן *rabbanan*. והוה יתיב
על גבי קרקע *v'havah yativ al gabi karka*, and he was sitting
straight on the ground. אמרו ליה *Amru leih*, so they said to
him, ליתיב מר אקרים וכסתות *Leitiv mar akkarim u'khastot*. You know, it's
not appropriate, the master should sit on pillows.
לא קיבל עליה *Lo kibeil aleih*. So the end of the verse
is, right, אשר לדוד יושב בשבת *asher l'David Yoshev baShevet*, and then
the next word is תחכמוני *Tachkemoni*. So תחכמוני
*Tachkemoni*, it should make me wise. So אמר רב rabbi, *Amar Rav*,
אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא *amar lo Hakadosh Baruch Hu*, הואיל והשפלת
עצמך *ho'il v'hishpalta atzmecha*, since you have lowered yourself, תהא כמוני *Tehei
chamoni*. So as opposed to תחכמוני *Tachkemoni*, right, as of wise, it's
meaning תהא כמוני *Tehei chamoni*. You now will have the power to
be like me. You were at the high position, you made yourself
low, the מידה כנגד מידה *mida k'neged mida* is that you now
have great power. Okay, שאני גוזר גזירה ואתה מבטלה gezeirah v'atah mevatlah.
*she'ani gozer gezeirah v'attah mevattelah*. And this is the tie-in to what
we were saying, if I were to make a גזירה *gezeirah*, you
now have the power to negate it. What?
Where do we see that?
I don't know. ראש השלישים *Rosh haShalishim*. So and the end of
the, so now again, we're explaining each word of the verse, right?
יושב בשבת *Yoshev baShevet*, תחכמוני *Tachkemoni*, ראש השלישים *Rosh haShalishim*. What's ראש
השלישים *Rosh haShalishim*? תהא ראש לשלשלת אבות *Tehei rosh l'shalshelet avot*. You
will be the head of the of the threefold braid, the three
fathers. Okay, so what does that mean exactly? So רבינו גרשום *Rabbeinu
Gershom* says you go before them in עולם הבא *Olam HaBa*. Alright.
הוא עדינו העצני *Hu Adino
haEtzni*. Again,
quoting a section of the verse. So what does that mean? כשהיה
יושב ועוסק בתורה היה מעדן עצמו *keshehayah yoshev v'osek baTorah hayah m'aden
atzmo*. So עדינו *Adino*, he would be כתולעת *katola'at*. He would make
himself pleasant, not עדינו *Adino* could also be like עידונים *iddunim*, like
you know a luxuriate, but here it means he would make himself
soft, you know, like a worm, lowly like a worm. He would
not, as we already see, was sitting on the ground, he wouldn't
hold of his status, he would lower himself. ובשעה שיוצא למלחמה *U'v'sha'ah
sheyotzei l'milchamah*, but when he would go off to war and that
needed strength, היה מקשה עצמו כעץ *hayah maksheh atzmo k'eitz*. So that's
עדינו *Adino*, who's soft, and העצני *haEtzni* like an עץ *eitz*, he'd
be strong as wood. Okay. על שמונה מאות חלל *Al shmoneh meiot
chalal*. So on 800 carcass, like a corpse. בפעם אחת *B'fa'am echat*.
שהיה זורק חץ ומפיל שמונה מאות
חלל בפעם אחת *shehayah zorek cheitz u'mapil shmoneh meiot chalal b'fa'am echat*.
על שמונה מאות חלל בפעם אחת *Al shmoneh meiot chalal b'fa'am echat*,
he would throw one arrow and it would kill 800 people in
one you know in one moment. והיה מתאנח *V'hayah mit'ane'ach*, and even
when that would happen he would be bemoaning על מאתיים *al matayim*,
200 of his men that died, even though it was 800 that
he had killed. דכתיב *Dikh'tiv*, איכה ירדוף אחד אלף *eichah yirdof echad
elef*, one should chase a thousand. And here 800 of the enemy
died but 200 of his own men, so the thousand was not
completely on the other side. יצתה בת קול ואמרה *Yatzta bat kol
v'amrah*, the heavenly voice came out and said: רק בדבר אוריה החתי
rak bidvar Uriyah haChiti. *rak bidvar Uriyah haChitti*. Ah, if you want
to know why it's not the full fulfillment of the prophecy, it's
because of the sin of אוריה החתי Uriyah haChiti. *Uriyah haChitti*. Okay,
so by the way, before we just continue, so that was a
fascinating little digression about דוד *David* and about צדיק גוזר *tzaddik gozer*.
even of his own men. So the thousand was not completely on
the other side, so יצתה בת קול ואמרה, the heavenly voice came
out and said רק בדבר אוריה החתי. Ah, if you want to
know why it's not the full fulfillment of the prophecy, it's because
of the sin of אוריה החתי. Okay, so by the way, before
we just continue, so that was a fascinating little digression about דוד
and about צדיק גוזר והקדוש ברוך הוא מקיים, but I want to
point out something that might be lost without that, that what we
do have is how דוד actually did not hold himself up in
terms of his status of כבוד. kavod. He lowered himself to the
floor, he actually was makes himself soft when it came to matters
of תורה, Torah. holding himself strong was in matters of the war,
although sometimes in the גמרא Gemara you have the מלחמתה של תורה,
milchamta shel Torah, and the גמרא Gemara speaks about like a harsher
and type of an approach, but again within these stories of the
rabbis being protective of their כבוד kavod and you know being harsh
and so on, right we have that דוד is very non-protective of
his כבוד, kavod, and the response is that God says, "That will
afford you even more power or more honor, you know, I'll now
make a גזירה ואתה מבטלה." So one does wonder if this is
being positioned as a counter-voice. Even as though point out correctly, even
the stories of נזיפה nezifah were you know the rabbis sort of
softening their approach to the harsher נידוי niduy and now you have
this story of דוד מלך ישראל, David Melech Yisrael, right and interesting
again thinking about the parallel to the רבי יהודה Yehuda הנשיא stories
who is completely מוחל mochel on his כבוד kavod and in the
end like, you know, told you'll get even a greater reward in
the end. So I sort of see this in conversation with the
earlier discussion.
Yeah this whole page in a way as an anti-קשייא kashya diatribe.
Right, starting with the נזיפה nezifah and then continuing. Right.
Not from the outside. Right.
Okay yes.
Because he is used pejoratively in that first context and he here
is the teacher of אבוה. Abua.
Oh so the word איה iya by חייא Chiya and here איה
iya by דוד which is so interesting. Okay, okay. אמר רב תנחום...
Amar Rav Tanchum... yeah the...
this is against the... the פשט pshat right? I mean דוד does
take things personally. Yes, well said.
Okay, אמר רב תנחום בריה דרבי חייא איש כפר עכו אמר רבי
יעקב בר אחא אמר רבי שמלאי ואמרי לה אמר רב תנחום אמר
רב הונא ואמרי לה אמר רב הונא לחודיה. Amar Rav Tanchum breih
d'Rabbi Chiya ish Kefar Akko amar Rabbi Yaakov bar Acha amar Rabbi
Simlai v'amrei lah amar Rav Tanchum amar Rav Huna v'amrei lah amar
Rav Huna lachudei. Okay so we had this tradition said and some
say רב הונא Rav Huna himself said the following. Top of יז
עמוד א. Yud Zayin Amud Aleph. Today's דף daf was ten minutes
ago. Let's see if we'll finish. תלמיד שנידה לכבודו נידויו נידוי. Talmid
shenidah lichvodo niduyo niduy. So now although we have just got through
נזיפה nezifah and not standing on your honor, we're back to being
putting somebody in נידוי לכבודו. niduy lichvodo. We had this idea before
right? מנודה לרב מנודה לתלמיד Menudah l'rav menudah l'talmid as opposed to
putting somebody in נידוי niduy because of a general offense and you're
just the person who witnessed it, you're putting somebody in נידוי niduy
because you personally were offended now not because you're a guy on
the street but if you're somebody who you know who has to
protect their rabbinic honor and authority, you're a רב rav who was
offended, but still it was a personal offense so you put them
in a personal state of נידוי, niduy, not in a universal state
of נידוי, niduy, a more subjective state of נידוי. niduy. And that's
this idea of נידה לכבודו nidah lichvodo for your honor that was
offended.
Okay so תלמיד שנידה לכבודו נידויו נידוי. talmid shenidah lichvodo niduyo niduy.
So even if you're a student or not a yet you know
you don't have סמיכה smicha yet, you're not a full רב, rav
nevertheless it still is you're in a place to put somebody in
נידוי niduy if they're not treating you with respect. דתניא D'tanya we
learned in a ברייתא braita מנודה לרב מנודה לתלמיד מנודה לתלמיד אינו
מנודה לרב. menudah l'rav menudah l'talmid, menudah l'talmid eino menudah l'rav. So
if the רב rav puts somebody in נידוי niduy the תלמידים talmidim
observe it, but if the תלמיד talmid does the רב rav doesn't
observe it. So the רב rav, doesn't observe it. The גמרא Gemara
says לרב הוא דאינו מנודה. l'rav hu d'eino menudah. The רב doesn't
have to observe it. It was the תלמיד talmid doing it on
a personal level. בהא לכולי עלמא B'ha l'chulei alma everybody else you
know מנודה menudah has to observe that state of נידוי niduy for
that you know in the way they interact with that person. Now
למאי? L'mai? Now for what reason did this תלמיד talmid put this
person into נידוי? niduy? אי במילי דשמיא Ei b'millei d'shmaya if it's
for matters of heaven which meaning like a basic religious concerns that's
not specific to him and his honor but this person is acting
in a general let's say derogatory way towards rabbis in general you
know other types of things which are you know
challenging to religious authority or to God's you know God's תורה. Torah
Yeah but it doesn't just mean transgression, the word is like מזלזל
mezalzel you know a way of despair you know contempt and disparaging
and something that really threatens the authority. So if that's the
issue אין חכמה ואין תבונה ואין עצה לנגד ה'. ein chochmah v'ein
tevunah v'ein eitzah leneged Hashem. There's you know there's no sense of
status and wisdom or whatever vis-a-vis God. Meaning status doesn't matter, everybody
even a תלמיד talmid puts somebody in נידוי niduy if this person
had done something that is a universal offense you know an objective
offense then everybody has to observe that נידוי niduy right? Because this
you know that's not specific to this תלמיד. talmid. אלא לאו לכבוד
עצמו Ela lav lichvod atzmo it must be it was not some
broader offense, it was something that was the honor he showed to
this person meaning generally this guy respects rabbis of course I have
respect for rabbis, you I don't respect.
So he acted disrespectful to this one person, it doesn't demonstrate a
larger disrespect, it demonstrates his relationship to this person. But nevertheless it
was disrespectful and this person's a rabbi. But that's a much more
limited sort of subjective type of a נידוי. niduy. Okay אמר and
therefore that's when... And that's called being מנדה לכבוד עצמו, menadeh l'kvod
atzmo, and then it's not universal, you know, the רבי doesn't have
to practice it, only other people have to practice it. Okay.
אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, said Rav Yosef, צורבא מרבנן עביד
דינא לנפשיה במילי דפסיקא ליה, tzurba m'rabbanan avid dina l'nafshei b'milei d'psika
lei, a member of the academy, you know, which is what צורבא
מרבנן tzurba m'rabbanan means, so it's not necessarily yet a full state
of being a רב, but it's a member, it's certainly a higher
stage than being a תלמיד, talmid, a member of the academy can
make a ruling for himself in something that is clear to him,
black and white to him. Now, what does this mean? This can
be a very dangerous statement because the phrase of עביד דינא לנפשיה,
avid dina l'nafshei, if anybody knows בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, taking the
law into your own hands, right? So, if you look at רבנו
גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, עביד דינא לנפשיה דאמר ליה את מחייבת לי הכי
והכי. avid dina l'nafshei d'amar lei at mechayves li hachi v'hachi. So,
basically here I am,
I'm having a little debate with Michael, and I say look Michael,
I learned חושן משפט, Choshen Mishpat, I know the הלכה, halacha, I
know that you owe me a hundred dollars and I'm just going
to take the hundred dollars from you. Okay, 'cause I know the
הלכה halacha and I'm a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and I can
פסקן pasken for myself. So, there is obviously, saying that is extremely
dangerous. Like, whatever happened to the fact that people are obviously not
able to be objective about their own cases and you can't פסקן
pasken for a relative, let alone for yourself? And you need an
outside party? Even if you know the הלכה, halacha, doesn't mean you're
interpreting the facts correctly, right? So the הרא"ש ha-Rosh basically says that
this is, I'll just read you one line in the הרא"ש ha-Rosh
where he actually points out how dangerous it is to read this
גמרא Gemara in that פשט pshat way or in that particular interpretation.
He says, here's the line, he says, where is it? Let me
just find it.
Yes, he says like this. He says וקשה הדבר לפרש כן. v'kashe
hadavar l'fareish kein. How can you explain it that way? אם הדין
ברור לו אינו ברור לאחרים וחילול השם הדבר. im hadin barur lo
eino barur l'acherim v'chilul Hashem hadavar. Number one is that I might
know the הלכה, halacha, but everybody else doesn't know the הלכה halacha
and if I'm ruling for myself, people just think I'm like you
know stealing, unless I'm doing something that's actually warranted, you know? They
just see me taking the money from Michael. ועוד אף שהדבר ברור
אין אדם דן דינו של קרובו וכל שכן של עצמו. v'od af
shehadavar barur ein adam dan dino shel krovo v'chol sheken shel atzmo.
You know, a, even if you're right, it's obviously very bad you
know in the perception issues, in the communal issues and so on,
and b, you're not necessarily being objective. Okay. So then what he
actually says this means is it means very much in the context
of what we're talking about before, about making a נידוי niduy for
your own כבוד. kavod. That you basically can you know can act
on your own to put somebody in נידוי niduy if you have
been offended. Of course then he says, well then what's it adding
to what we said before? And what does it mean דינא פסיקא
ליה? dina psika lei? So he tries to figure out exactly some
nuance that it's adding to what is said before. But reading it
in the פשט pshat way is
very you know is very disturbing. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
continues and says the following: ההוא צורבא מרבנן דהוו סנו שומעניה. hahu
tzurba m'rabbanan de-havu sanu shumanei. There was a certain member of the
academy who had a bad reputation. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda,
so Rav Yehuda said, היכי דנעביד? heichi di-na'avid? What should we do
about this person? נשמתיה? neshamtei? Should we put him in נידוי? niduy?
Here's the question, right? How do you act when a rabbi's acting
incorrectly?
Should we put him in נידוי? niduy? צריכי ליה רבנן. tzrichi lei
rabbanan. The other rabbis need him, like you know, he was not
standard רבנן is on the lower level than צורבא מרבנן. tzurba m'rabbanan.
So you know, he was somebody that maybe gave שיעור shiur or
something and he was so he's in a position of you know
of influence or certainly
that people needed him. You know, that's also often why people are
afraid to act when rabbis are acting incorrectly because you know all
the good that he's doing in the community and all these other
types of things, so they didn't want to do anything. לא נשמתיה,
Lo neshamtei, but if we do not put him in נידוי, niduy,
קא מיתחל שמא דשמיא, ka mitchal shma de-shmaya, חילול השם chilul Hashem
that this person can act this way and with impunity. And we're
going to find out later there were questions about basically, so things
nothing really changes, there were issues about sexual improprieties, you know? So
what does that say when your rabbi acts that way and what
does it do to represent תורה Torah and so on? So it's
like you know and this is exactly the way people the types
of you know realities people find themselves in, right? And why they're
often reluctant to act, and on the other hand the חילול שם
שמים chilul shem shamayim that results from not from not voicing protest
and acting properly. אמרו ליה לרמי בר אבא, amru lei l'Rami bar
Abba, so they said to Rami bar Abba, מידי שמיע לך בהא?
midi shmia lach b'ha? Have you heard anything regarding this? אמר ליה,
Amar lei, how to deal with this case? הכי אמר רבי יוחנן,
Hachi amar Rabbi Yochanan, מאי דכתיב, mai d'chtiv, what's meant by the
verse, כי שפתי כהן ישמרו
דעת ותורה יבקשו מפיהו? ki siftei kohen yishmeru da'at v'Torah yivakshu mipihu?
The lips of the kohen will observe knowledge and they will seek
out תורה Torah instruction from his mouth. כי מלאך ה' צבאות הוא,
ki malach Hashem tzevaot hu, 'cause he's the angel of God. אם
דומה הרב למלאך ה' יבקשו תורה מפיהו. im domeh ha-rav l'malach Hashem
yivakshu torah mipihu. If the rabbi is like the angel of God,
then he should be teaching תורה Torah and you should seek it
out. ואם לאו אל יבקשו תורה מפיהו. v'im lav al yivakshu torah
mipihu. And if not, don't, which basically means it's very... it's very
nice that he gives a great גמרא Gemara שיעור shiur but if
he's
not gives a nice sermon on שבת Shabbos but if he's got
a questionable character then you can't bracket the questionable character. That's a
rabbi has to represent תורה and morality and obviously he should not
be functioning in that role. And don't let that
certainly prevent you from acting the way you're supposed to act in
regards to him. So what does it do? So the גמרא Gemara
says fine. שמתיה Shamtei רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, so רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda put him in חרם, cherem, in נידוי. nidui. איחלש Ichlash רב
יהודה. Rav Yehuda. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda got sick. Now you might
think this is a story that he got sick because he acted
incorrectly, but that's not going to be the story. איחלש Ichlash
רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. אתו רבנן לשיולי ביה, Atu rabanan lishuyiley bey,
the rabbis, meaning also like more like the rabbinic students, the anonymous
רבנן, came
to seek after his welfare. They came to pay
a ביקור חולים bikur cholim call. ואתא איהו נמי בהדייהו, Va'atu ihu
nami bahadyu, this rabbi that was put in נידוי, nidui, he came
amongst in the group of them. כד חזייה Kad chazyei רב יהודה,
Rav Yehuda, when רב יהודה Rav Yehuda saw this one guy, חייך,
chiech, he laughed. אמר ליה, Amar ley, so the rabbi who had
been put in נידוי nidui said, לא מסתייך דשמתיה לההוא גברא, lo
mistayecha deshamtei lahu gavra, is it not enough that you put me
in נידוי, nidui, ואחוכיי נמי מחייכת בי, ve'achuchuy nami mechayechat bi, and
you're laughing at me? אמר ליה, Amar ley, so רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda said, לאו בדידך מחייכנא, lav bididach mechayechana, I'm not laughing at
you, אלא דכי אזלינא לההוא עלמא בדיחא דעתאי, ella dechi azlina lehu
alma bidicha da'tai, but I'm smiling, I'm happy that when I go
to that future world, or maybe he's already been going to that
future world, taking little visits, because that's where he's going, he's going
to die soon anyway, you know, I'm in a very joyous mood.
Why? דאפילו לגברא כוותך, De'afilu legavra kevasach, even somebody like you, a
man of influence and power and that people look up to, לא
חניפי ליה, lo chanif lei, I did not, I wasn't מחניף, machnif,
I didn't flatter you, I didn't give deference to your status when
somebody had to stand up and say something and say that you
weren't acting right. So I, and I feel very good
about the fact that I kept to that conviction and I'll see
my reward in the world to come. נח נפשיה דרב יהודה. deRav
Yehuda. Then רב יהודה Rav Yehuda died. Now again, you could have
read this whole story that he acted wrong. Like, I mean, the
story is he put him in נידוי, nidui, he died. But anyway,
but the גמרא's framing it as no, he's about to die and
he's still very proud that he did what he needed to be
done and he didn't, so אתא לבי מדרשא. ata lebei midrasha. So
the rabbi who had been put in נידוי nidui came to the
בית מדרש. Beis Medrash.
אמר להו, Amar lehu, שרו לי, sharu li, he said to the
rabbis, release me from this נידוי. nidui. Gets back to the other
question of who can release somebody from a נידוי. nidui. אמרו ליה
רבנן, Amru lei rabanan, so the rabbis said, גברא דחשיב כרב יהודה
ליכא הכא דלישרי לך. gavra dechashiv keRav Yehuda leka hacha delishri lach.
We don't have somebody of equal weight of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
that can release you. אלא זיל לגבי דרב יהודה נשיאה דלישרי לך,
Ella zil legabei deRav Yehuda Nesia delishri lach, go to רב יהודה
נשיאה, Rav Yehuda Nesia, which was the grandson of רבי, that he'll
release you. He's a נשיא. nasi. Again, the power of the נשיא.
nasi. אזל לקמיה, Azal lekamei, he went to him. אמר ליה לרבי
אמי, Amar ley leRebbe Ami, פוק עיין בדיניה, puk ayin bedineih,
go look into the matter, see whether we could or we should
release him. אי מיבעי למשרי ליה שרו ליה, I miba'ei lemishrei lei
sharu lei, if it's appropriate to release him, release him, release him.
עיין רבי אמי בדיניה, Ayin Rebbe Ami bedineih, רבי אמי Rebbe Ami
looked into this. סבר למשרי ליה, Savar lemishrei lei,
he figured yeah, whatever, he's suffered enough, whatever, he figured we would
release him. אמר רב שמואל בר נחמני על רגלוהי, Amar Rav Shmuel
bar Nachmani al raglohi, רב שמואל בר נחמני Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani
stood on his feet and he said, ומה שפחה של בית רבי,
umah shifcha shebeis Rebbe, the שפחה shifcha of רבי's house, which by
the way was רב יהודה נשיאה's Rav Yehuda Nesia grandfather, even the
שפחה shifcha of רבי's house לא נהגו חכמים קלות ראש בנידוייה, lo
nahalu chachamim kal rosh beniduyah, when she put somebody in נידוי, nidui,
the rabbis did not treat that lightly. שלש שנים, Shelosh shanim, for
three years they let that נידוי nidui stand and we'll hear that
story in a little bit. יהודה חבירינו, Yehuda chavreinu, יהודה our colleague,
על אחת כמה וכמה, al achas kamma vechamma, how much more so
if he put this person in נידוי nidui that we should not
be quick to release him. אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rebbe Zeira, מאי
דקמא דאתא האידנא האי סבא לבי מדרשא, mai dekama de'asa idna hai
sava levei midrasha, what happened
that דוקא davka today this elder, you know רב שמואל בר נחמני
Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani happened to show up in the בית מדרש
Beis Medrash דלא אתא לבי מדרשא הא כמה שני, delo ata levei
midrasha ha kamma shani, where
he hasn't been in the בית מדרש Beis Medrash for many years?
דוקא Davka today he showed up in the בית מדרש Beis Medrash
and he lodged this protest when we were discussing this issue. שמע
מינה לא מיבעי למשרי ליה, Shema mina lo miba'ei lemishrei lei,
so obviously it's a סימן מן השמים siman min hashamayim that he
happened to show up today and he's voicing this protest and we
should pay attention to the protest and it's not appropriate to release
this person from his vow. לא שרו ליה, Lo sharu lei, they
didn't release him from, not the vow, from the נידוי. nidui. They
didn't release him. נפק, Nafak, he went out. כי קא בכי ואזיל,
Ki ka bachi ve'azil, he was crying as he was leaving. אתא
זיבורא וטרקיה אאמתיה, Ata zibura ve'tarkei a'amateih, came a wasp and stung
him on his
genitals. ושכיב, ushach ve'nimis, and he died as a result.
עיילוהו למערתא דחסידי, ayluyei lemarta dechasidai, they wanted to bring him into
the cave of חסידים, chasidim, interesting with all of this, his bad
report and being in נידוי, nidui, and before we were בית סוקלין
על ארונו, beis soklin al arono,
here we hear that he obviously was still a great rabbi, so
they wanted to bring him into this cave called the מערתא דחסידי,
marta dechasidai, cave of חסידים. chasidim. ולא קיבלוהו, v'lo kibluhu, somehow the
cave didn't receive him, whatever that means. תוספות Tosfos says there was
like you know a like a serpent at the mouth of the
stay of the cave which we hear in other stories.
איילו למערתא דדייני, ayilu l'marata de'dayanei, they brought him to the cave
of judges, וקיבלוהו, v'kibluhu, and there he was accepted because he was
a judge, but he wasn't a חסיד, chasid, he obviously there was
some issue about his bad reputation and why he was put into
נידוי. nidui. Now, מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what is the reason? דעביד
כרבי אילעאי, de'avid ke'Rabbi Ilai, he did like רבי אילעאי, Rabbi Ilai,
דתניא dtanya we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, רבי אילעאי אומר, Rabbi
Ilai omer, רבי אילעאי Rabbi Ilai says, אם רואה אדם שיצרו מתגבר
עליו, im ra'ah adam she'yitzro misgaber alav, if a person sees that
his יצר הרע, yetzer hara, specifically it's in the context of sexual
desire is having power over him and he's not going to be
able to subdue it, ילך למקום שאין מכירין אותו, yeilech lemakom she'ein
makirin oto, go to a place where nobody recognizes you, him, וילבש
שחורים ויתעטף שחורים, v'yilbash shechorim v'yit'atef shechorim, dress in black, wrap yourself
in black, meaning A either so nobody recognizes you, and B maybe
so it humbles you and maybe it'll reverse your course, and ויעשה
מה שלבו חפץ, v'ya'aseh mah shelibo chafetz, and if you still have
to act, fine, you'll act and do the way your heart desires,
but at least it will respect, you know, at least it will
be a way in which you're,
you know, it's not like a חילול השם. chilul Hashem. Nobody, you
know, knows who you are. So where were we? מה שלבו חפץ.
mah shelibo chafetz. Did I skip a line? ואל יחלל שם שמים
בפרהסיא, v'al yachalel shem shamayim b'farhesya, and it wouldn't be a public
חילול השם. chilul Hashem. Now, what does this mean in the context
of this story? So תוספות Tosfos has two גרסאות. girsaos. One גרסא
girsa is, why was he accepted into the cave of דיינים? dayanim?
If he really had a bad reputation and he really was in
נידוי, nidui, why was he accepted in the cave? And the answer
is, because even though he did sin sexually, right, he at least
did it in a way that somewhat was protective of שם שמים
shem shamayim and he did it and he went into hiding in
private, obviously in a way some people heard something about it because
he had a bad reputation, but actually in a way that he
at least dealt with it in as responsible of a way as
possible if he was anyway going to go ahead and sin. And
that's why he was accepted into the cave. The other version is
not why was he accepted into the cave of דיינים, dayanim, but
why wasn't he accepted into the cave of חסידים? chasidim? And the
answer is not דעביד כרבי אילעאי, de'avid ke'Rabbi Ilai, he did like
רבי אילעאי, Rabbi Ilai, but דעבר על רבי אילעאי. de'avar al Rabbi
Ilai. He didn't do what רבי אילעאי Rabbi Ilai said and he
didn't go into some foreign city and do it in disguise, he
did it in public. Now, this raises interesting questions, right? Because on,
you know, it's on the one hand you have the aspect of
חילול השם, chilul Hashem, you know, but you have hypocritical and you're
pretending and so on. But, you know, there's a real power to
this not only protecting public perception, but sort of sending signals to
yourself that what you're doing is, you know, something obvious wrong and
a violation and so on. You know, רבי ישראל סלנטר Rav Yisrael
Salanter says the famous line, the גמרא says if somebody does something
once it's, you know, you know, does a איסור issur twice, it's
נעשה לו כהיתר. na'aseh lo k'heter. And רבי ישראל סלנטר Rav Yisrael
Salanter said and if you do it three times, it's נעשה לו
כמצוה. na'aseh lo k'mitzvah. So,
you know, so doing it in this way, now you could, you
know, is a way that you're constantly sort of sending a signal
and you're acknowledging that yes, I'm transgressing and I know it's wrong
and I know that I have to therefore, you know, do it
in this way, as opposed to somehow trying to rationalize it. The
opposite argument could be that that maybe you think you feel you
have more license to do it because nobody's knowing about it and
you're doing it in private. רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein was
asked a question in the old days when people who wanted to
go see pornography had to actually go to a movie theater to
do it. רב משה Rav Moshe was asked the question about somebody
who said that he can't control his יצר הרע, yetzer hara, should
he take off his יארמולקע yarmulke before going into the theater or
not? And I believe, if I remember רב משה'ס Rav Moshe's response,
he said don't. By keeping on your יארמולקע yarmulke yes there's a
problem of חילול השם, chilul Hashem, but hopefully it'll shame you into
rethinking, you know, what you're, so it's interesting two sides of the
coin in terms of this whole issue. Okay, but anyway here's the
person and obviously what the wasp bit stung him, there were issues
going around and there were reasons he was in נידוי, nidui, but
it was a sort of a complicated type of a situation. The
last point I'll say is, notice by the way that even though
he was in נידוי, nidui, he came with the group of Rabbis
to pay a ביקור חולים bikur cholim call. Somebody in נידוי, nidui,
you're not supposed to sit in ד' אמות. arba amos. You know,
you're not supposed to make him sort of part of a group,
eat with him. So you might think you're not supposed to go
pay a ביקור חולים bikur cholim call with a group of Rabbis
together with him. So it raises also interesting questions of the limits
of how much separation exists, you know, within that context of being
in a state of נידוי. nidui. Okay, they continued to תמוז. Tammuz.